# **Ashraful Islam**

ashrafulrafi@gmail.com (929) 421-8226 Birmingham, AL, USA github.com/ashraful-islam-rafi linkedin.com/in/ashraful-islam-rafi Python, Java, C, C++, PHP, Racket, JavaScript

# Summary

Computer Science graduate student at the University of Alabama at Birmingham (UAB) with over 2 years of academic research experience and over 7 years of industry experience taking on roles such as Software Engineer, and Programmer.

#### **Education**

### University of Alabama at Birmingham | Alabama, USA

Jan 2022 - Dec 2024

• M.S. in Computer Science

## **Leading University** | Sylhet, Bangladesh

Aug 2009 - Aug 2013

B.Sc. In Computer Science & Engineering

# **Experience**

# Graduate Research Assistant | UAB | Alabama, USA

Jan 2022 - August 2024

- Brouhaha (Prototype Research Compiler): Led a team of three students in developing Brouhaha, which currently outperforms other compilers like Chicken and Guile, achieving 3x better running times for certain benchmarks. This performance primarily results from performing control flow analysis (k-CFA) to detect function inlining opportunities.
- Compiler: Wrote a functional compiler in Racket that translates minimal Racket code into C++.

#### Software Engineer | BANGLA SEARCH ENGINE (PIPILIKA) | Sylhet, Bangladesh

Aug 2017 - Mar 2021

- Search Relevancy Improvement: Enhanced keyword-based search relevancy by 35% through redesigning the Apache Solr schema, extracting Bangla Unicode data, and implementing Solr's dismax query parser.
- Large-Scale Data Search Portal: Developed a generic approach using **Scrapy** to crawl, parse, and index unstructured data from over 40,000 websites, boosting indexed data by 18% and enhancing search capabilities.
- Solr Analytic Library: Wrote RESTful API using **Spring Boot** to provide domain-specific time series data for Solr projects, improving reporting capabilities and reducing the debugging time by 20%.

#### **Programmer** | SOUTHEAST UNIVERSITY | Dhaka, Bangladesh

Apr 2015 - Aug 2017

- Served over 3 months as the in-charge of the Information Technology (IT) department, managing all IT operations and ensuring efficient and effective technology solutions across the organization.
- Introduced an Online Admission System using PHP, MySQL, and Bootstrap3, contributing to 25% of total admissions.
- Improved the University Support System software report generation time by 30% by redesigning the MySQL schema.
- Coordinated and monitored vendor company in developing Human Resources Management System (HRMS) software.

# Software Developer | IT LAB SOLUTIONS LTD | Sylhet, Bangladesh

Sep 2013 - Dec 2014

• Designed and developed customized web-based Shop Management software for over 5 different businesses using CodeIgniter and Bootstrap3 with MySQL as the database.

#### **Skills**

- Programming Languages: Python, Java, C, C++, PHP, Racket, JavaScript.
- Databases/Frameworks/Technologies: Spring Boot, REST API, Jsoup, Scrapy, Bootstrap3, Codeigniter, AJAX, MySQL, MongoDB, Apache Solr, HTML5, CSS3, Git, Docker, AWS, Maven, WordPress, SDLC, STLC, MVC, Agile, Scrum.

#### Extracurricular / Activities

- Judge: Served as a judge of the Summer 2023 Undergraduate Research Expo, UAB.
- Treasurer: Managed financial operations of the Bangladesh Student Association, a graduate student organization at UAB.
- Tutor: Conducted over 15 programming workshops focused on Data Structures and Algorithms at Leading University.